13 . October 2008 Received by Filmkameratene A / S
an anonymous shipment with two hard drives containing 283 minutes of footage .
This is a rough cut of the material ...
All is shown chronologically , and the images have not been manipulated .
For over a year a team of investigators studied
whether the material was real or not .
The conclusion was that it is genuine .
It 's clear . Turn on the radio .
- Johanna , do you have audio ? - Yes .
It doesn 't work .
Late yesterday evening bear tracks were found in Volda .
A team of bear hunters arrived early today in order to shoot the bear .
The leader of the hunters tells the following to the BBC :
This is a stray bear that we should kill pretty quickly .
But our real concern is a poacher , who has followed us here .
Only a select few are allowed to hunt bears .
I know absolutely all the bear hunters in Norway .
The guy in the Land Rover is certainly not a bear hunter .
If he shoots at the bear , he does it illegally .
- Have you seen him ? - We see him everywhere .
If I see him again , there will be consequences .
I think it 's a common poacher .
- What would you say to him ? - That he should lay his cards on the table .
Now !
- There are cars coming from every direction . - We 're going to lose him !
Ready ?
We only know that his name is Hans . We do not have his last name .
I think you need to be more serious .
What is he doing in Volda ? Who is this man ?
- Is there sound ? - You haven 't plugged it in .
You don 't get an interview with a damn poacher .
I don 't think it 's funny when you ridicule him .
That 's terrific . Thank You . Bye .
Thomas , he says he 's seen the guy and he lives at the trailer park !
I can 't say that I know him , but he lives here .
He lives there . Shall I show you ?
I don 't know what it is that stinks , but it stinks something horrible .
- What 's this for ? - I don 't know what it is ..
Thyme ?
He drives off and is gone until the sun comes up .
- He 's out all night ? - Yes . Always .
- Are you up for this ? - Yes .
We don 't know when he coming , if he 's even going to .
- There he is ! - The camera 's running . Ask him straight out .
Good morning . My name is Thomas . We are from the college in Volda .
May we ask you a couple of questions ?
Go away .
Maybe we can come back a bit later ...
- Are you recording anything ? - Hush , I hear something .
Yes , I 'm rolling now .
I expect to find it tonight . Ok . That 's Fine . Bye .
- He isn 't here . - He was right in front of us !
Yes , but ...
- Damn ! - Well done , Thomas .
- Are you filming ? Can you see anything ? - Yes .
There 's some kind of hairy stuff hanging from the ceiling .
And there 's a shotgun there .
We are heading to a place where a bear was found shot this morning .
Could it be him who shot the bear ?
Where this came from , Heaven knows .
I 've checked with all of the registered bear hunters .
None of them shot this bear .
All bear hunting is strictly regulated by the State .
So there is going to be a hell of a fuss when a bear is killed this way .
Come here .
These tracks here do not match with the bear 's .
I think someone brought the bear here and positioned it like this .
- It is quite strange . - Totally agree .
You are from the Wildlife Advisory Board , right ? Finn Haugan ?
The hunters say they don 't think it 's bear tracks .
That 's ridiculous . What kind of tracks would they be then ?
It 's a bear with bear tracks leading to it .
- Why do you think they doubt it ? - Ask them . It 's crazy .
We 've waited a few hours for Hans now . It seems like something 's brewing .
We are pretty confident that he is going somewhere .
Go !
It appears that he 's going on the ferry .
How long do you think we should keep this up ?
Can you see what it is ?
He 's carrying a car tire .
- What 's he doing ? - He disappeared down the hill .
Three , two , one and ...
Sogn og Fjordane !
Okay , he 's standing over there .
Just stay hidden .
We met briefly before .
- Really ? - Thomas from the University of Volda .
- Is it ... - So are you following me ?
No . We just want to ask you a few questions .
No .
Are you ...
What were you really doing in Volda ?
Was it you who shot the bear ?
Stay away from me ! Cut that out . Leave me alone !
First , we get what we need . Then we can go back .
It will be insanely good if we can get the guy to answer the questions .
We have tried , many times .
Do you think Michael Moore gave up after his first attempt ?
Left arm or right foot ? Kicking foot and ...
Now we have been here all afternoon .
He 's still in his car . I guess he 's sleeping .
We are patiently waiting for something to happen .
Are you kidding me ? Okay .
I have to take the audio equipment with us .
What is this ?
" No Trespassing . Blasting in progress . "
Did you see that ? Was it a road ?
Did you ?
Terrible roads .
You go first in cade there 's a group of inbred pig farmers .
- I 'm not ... - Stop whining .
- I should probably give my opinion here . - Should we go back ?
- We can drop the whole thing . - No !
Wait !
See here .
I don 't think he 's in the car .
- So we know that he 's here . - But what is he doing ?
Here 's a path .
- I hear something far away . - What is it ?
Troll !
Thomas !
Hurry ! The car 's right here !
- What ? - I was bitten !
- Are you okay ? - It stings .
- You heard him yell " troll " ? - Shut up .
You need more .
- What can I do ? - Get the dressing from the first aid kit .
- Not ... - We have to lift it up a little here .
Damnit . You look messed up , Thomas .
- What are you doing ? - Tetanus .
You yelled something in the woods , didn 't you ?
- You heard it , Johanna . - What 's the slime here ?
What did he say ?
- More ? - Yes .
Can we get a lift down to the car ?
It isn 't a good idea to follow me .
Did you yell " troll " back there ?
- Is this your car ? - What the hell is this ?
- What happened ? - It 's our car !
Someone smashed the car .
It 's totally wrecked .
Look here , Thomas .
- Do you understand any of this ? - Yes , I have some idea .
It 's not a bear that did this here ..
What do you think happened ?
- What ... - Ask whether it is a troll .
If you know what happened to the car , say so !
- You shouted " troll " in the woods . - Drop it now !
What the hell are you looking for ?
Will you film me if I say that there are trolls ?
- Is it funny ? - No , but you do not think there are ...
Now I drive . If you are going to ride along , you must come now .
What do we do ?
Do you have any bags ?
Just so we understand you correctly : You actually believe that there are trolls ?
Do you think it was a bear that bit you ?
Whats happening ?
Why did we stop ?
Thanks for letting us ride with you .
We would like to see what you are doing and film it .
Yes , we really would like to .
You can film when I kill the one who attacked you , on one condition :
You must do exactly as I say , no matter what I say . Okay ?
Yes .
I feel like I 'm bleeding everywhere .
- Can I take a look at the wound ? - It looks a little bit cool .
- You are sick in the head . - I mean it .
- Why did you call them ? - To say that we 're here .
He isn 't so dangerous . He 's just weird .
Remember that he 's running the show , and we do as he says .
So we get what we need .
Is there anyone here who believes in God or Jesus ?
No , none of us .
Don 't look at me .
Seriously ? Because they smell Christian blood ?
Is it okay ?
Go out and close the gate and hang up the sign in the middle .
- Is that a landmine you have there ? - Yes , but it is not armed .
I 'm sitting on a landmine ? Are you crazy ?
Is there anyone who won 't go into the woods with us ?
Someone who has changed his mind ? Who is afraid of trolls ?
- No . - No ? Good .
There is a creek there . Take your clothes off and wash yourself thoroughly .
- Especially underarms and groin . - No !
- Why ? - To remove all of your body odor .
Then rub your entire body with this . Your clothes as well .
- What is it ? - Trollstink .
- Put it on your whole body . - Are you messing with me ? It stinks !
You must smell like a troll or else they will smell you and run away .
For Satan !
- No , I say ! - It doesn 't bother me , Thomas .
No , I said !
You should do exactly as I say .
If you don 't do it , I will go up alone and you can stay here .
Do you understand ?
Are you ready ? Have you rubbed yourself ?
You look very cute .
Flashlights for you .
- What is it ? - A weapon , really .
Hans ? How do you use this weapon ?
It shoots out a strong burst of ultraviolet light .
UVB rays . Just like the sun or a tanning bed .
Don 't you know anything , Thomas ? They turn to stone in sunlight .
- Yes . Or they explode . - Didn 't you read anything ?
I heard the fairy tales when I was little , but ... Did you know , Kalle ?
What if the troll wants to have an eating match ?
An eating match ?
Asbjornsen and Moe 's stories were not entirely correct in reality .
I think it matches up fairly well .
- Troll Piss . - My God !
It smells quite pungent .
I 'm chasing a raglefant . There is piss everywhere up here .
Seems like he has been chased out of his territory . He marked it though .
He doesn 't seem well . I would like to find out what 's wrong .
A blood sample from the troll ?
I don 't have any equipment or anything .
You too . Bye .
I need help finding out what 's wrong .
Blood test , it ...
It will be difficult .
Who were you talking to ?
A veterinarian .
A veterinarian !
If you wait here , I 'll try to track down the troll and chase it .
Yeah . Was this what you imagined ?
It may take a little time .
It 's a shame for him if he really believe in trolls .
Maybe he was filming us .
- That must have certainly been it . - He 's sitting and laughing at us somewhere .
We are so stupid that we sit up here and ...
Cranberries ?
- In the woods ? - Yes , without food and drink .
- Great ! - What is it ?
It 's like a night-vision thing .
Listen !
It 's just the guy that ...
in one week was bitten by a bear .
- It 's a better story . - You look pretty good .
- So I think I chose it . - Being bitten by a bear ?
Can you feel it ?
There are some very strange sounds here .
What is it ?
Seriously . There 's something going on .
What 's happening ?
This is just a fucking joke .
It 's a damn Tusseladd ! Get away !
Run , dammit !
Hurry !
- Did you see that ? - Yes .
Where did it go ? Did you seen where it went ?
Get behind the car !
No !
- Give me the camera ! - No !
Where 's Johanna ?
Thomas ! Kalle !
- Johanna ! - It was real !
I said it ! I knew it !
They exist !
- Say something . - This rocks !
We ran through the entire forest ...
Why the hell did you say that you weren 't Christians ?
You didn 't know that trolls sniffed ? One of you believes in God .
I do not believe in God . I was in the YMCA .
But it was my parents who told me to do it .
I do not believe in God . Seriously .
- It 's not her . - What do you mean ?
Stop this nonsense ! It 's some genetically modified bastard creation .
- It is a troll . - No , it 's not !
Why is there no one who knows about all of this ?
Because someone wants it to be kept a secret .
The State ?
Keeping a State secret ? Do you work for the State ?
- Why would you show us this stuff now ? - It 's a fucking shitty job .
The Work Authority has said some things they shouldn 't have . I don 't get nights in .
No overtime and shitty pay .
Maybe it 's time for a change in troll management .
- If you manage to get this on TV ... - I think we 're going to .
Come on .
If you would like to see more of these creatures , it 's ok with me .
I would move away if I were you .
Damn !
The stone is crushed and given to anyone who has a hole to fill .
What the hell is that ?
- Who 's coming ? - I don 't know .
Hey , hey .
The guy we were filming ...
What are you doing , Hans ? Did these people film you ?
They wanted to see trolls , so I showed them some .
We have interviewed him before . Aren 't you from the Game Board ?
It was an exceptionally bad idea .
Turn off the camera . I have enough problems .
The valley is littered with dead cows .
We can not talk about this while they film . Turn off the camera . Now !
- Put it down . - We are allowed to film here .
- Are you starting to lose it ? - I have full control .
As soon as a scapegoat in place , I 'll take care of the rest .
Hi Finn . How are you ?
Going good ? Excellent ?
I 've driven a long way .
Wait . Are you filming ?
Really good ! Very fresh !
- It isn 't a Scandinavian bear . - No , it 's from Croatia !
It is very similar to the Scandinavian bear . No problem , Finn !
Hello !
It is very fresh .
We need to take a break . My back !
Put it over there .
Very good . It 's very good .
35.000 ... Bad bear , bad price .
Raglefanten is still in the woods .
Then go find it !
A pair of German tourists disappeared in the night .
- We expect there will be a couple more . - It 's not my problem .
If you think you that you get to keep the footage ... No Way !
Han is the best at finding bears .
This bear is from the zoo .
Zoo , you know .
- Why does Finn buy the bears ? - No idea !
In Poland we ask not , we do .
Why problem make when you no problem have you don 't want to make ?
- Goodbye ! - Goodbye .
It says , " Piot Painting Service . "
What is your job exactly ?
My job is to kill all the trolls who break out of their territories
and approach people . - How often do they break out ?
Very rarely , but now we have a special situation .
Many trolls have broken out and are wandering around the area .
Finn is a ... bureaucrat .
He directs the TST . His role is primarily to prevent
people from finding out about the trolls in the forest .
In a way , you are probably some of Norway 's greatest heroes .
No , you 're wrong .
What I do is not heroic . It 's dirty , hard work .
How is it possible that nobody knows about this ?
Let 's drive to Oslo , to sell these recordings to the BBC , and get lots of money .
That isn 't relevant right now . Now we just follow him .
Finn is angry .
- What should we do now ? - It 's time for breakfast .
- You should eat something . - I 'm not that hungry .
I 'm a little ... tired .
How many types of trolls are there ?
There are two main groups : mountain trolls and forest trolls .
The subgroups are raglefant , tusseladd , rimtusse ...
Dovregubben .
Harding is the type on the West Coast .
But the troll we saw ...
Do they all have three heads ?
No , they 're all different .
They develop heads through their life cycle .
They are not born with three heads .
Usually they are born with one head , and the others grow later .
They only have eyes on the middle head . It 's their original one .
The other heads are not really minds , but formations -
- To simulate heads and scare other trolls .
Or impress female trolls .
What is that form ?
- What is the TST ? - Troll Security Team
Every time we harvest a troll , we have to fill this out .
Where we kill it , its sex and whether it exploded or was calcified .
In Asbjornsen and Moe fables , the trolls have clothes
and talk like humans .
- They are like people . - You can forget those stories .
Trolls are animals . Predators .
They eat , shit , mate with and devour everything around them .
- How long do they live ? - 1000 , 1200 years .
- How intelligent are they ? - Not smart at all . They 're stupid .
They manage to find food , but when you eat rocks , it isn 't hard to survive .
I saw one who tried to eat its own tail .
He had his head between his legs and tried to grab his tail .
When he had swallowed almost the entire thing
he toppled over and rolled down the hill like a wheel .
- I was in the Navy . - Was that how you got the job ?
No , they were looking for someone who could ...
- So you 're the only one in Norway ? - Yes .
Shall we go ?
- They eat all kinds of crap . - They eat people ?
- You can try to offer yourself of course . - No , but they have been eating people ?
- Are those troll tails ? - Yes . Some are parts and some are whole .
- Why ? - So it smells like troll .
Why does it need to smell like troll ?
I must be able to get close to the trolls without them noticing me .
- A tanning bed ? - Yes .
- It can give you skin cancer . - I use sunscreen .
I have a little trouble sleeping at night .
- Is that what we smeared ourselves with ? - Yes .
- What is it ? - Concentrated troll smell .
A mixture of everything bad that can be squeezed out of a troll .
We must find raglefanten before he eats through every house in the area .
The German tourists were found north of Kulp Mountain , killed by a bear .
Finn Haugan from the Wildlife Board will examine whether it was the same ...
Do you know where the troll might be ? Do you have any clues ?
No .
What are you looking for ?
Landslides , fallen trees and such .
Do you see anything ?
- Is it like that ? Only with a backpack . - Yes .
Maybe you should check it ?
- Is it bad ? - It goes up and down .
- Is it safe here ? - They are only out at night .
Kalle , we can not ...
It is hasn 't left , but the bait is gone . Probably taken by small trolls .
Concrete and charcoal is an unbeatable combination .
- Do it now ! - Now ?
Now , Hans has found traces of what he thinks is raglefanten ...
Hans has found traces of what he thinks is raglefanten .
And there is a sheep carcass nearby .
He thinks that there is some correlation between these two things .
Hurry !
Global warming has caused certain things to happen
with our fauna , our flora , with wildlife ...
The tracks you see here in the area
are from a Russian bear , who has come through Finland and Sweden .
The bear stores his food under the bridge here .
- Isn 't that strange behavior ? - Not for a Russian bear .
They are accustomed to long , harsh winters . So they hoard like squirrels .
Isn 't there something strange about the bear tracks ?
There 's the outer toe , so it 's the left foot . And then you have the right foot here .
Has the bear been like that , or ?
You have seen bear tracks before , right ?
Hey , what about the tracks ?
He has stripped the bark of the tree . Typical raglefant .
He 'll be back tonight . I have something to lure him with .
- And then you 'll kill him ? - Yes .
But first I must take the blood test .
Is this a syringe ?
That 's absolutely terrible ! It 's animal abuse .
It isn 't cruelty . It 's just bait .
It 's too far away . Can 't we go further ?
No , I 'm zoomed in . We can see it very well .
Odd working hours .
We have been here forever . It isn 't even certain that troll is coming .
- We are fine here . We 're doing fine . - But we can see much better from there .
Let 's go .
It 's here .
Can you hear it ?
Run !
Damn , I hate it here !
Now you have to keep a good distance . I 'll pour a little Christian blood out .
Pull back !
Damn ! Kalle ! Thomas !
Move ! Move !
Are you okay ? You ...
Are you okay ?
Help him up .
- Come on , Hans . - Are you okay ?
Be careful with the red button .
Give me the syringe .
Stay up there .
So we know that trolls also explode .
- How are you ? - Yes please .
Not so bad .
Just a little stiff .
A little stiff ?
This is so sick !
At least I got the blood test .
I 'll be there in half an hour , I think . That 's fine . Goodbye .
You look like a newborn !
These are some young filmmakers . They will ask you some questions .
- Is that blood ? - Yes .
- A bit of a fuss to get the sample . - I can see that .
Look at you guys !
- Gladly ! - There is a toilet in there .
- What do you see ? - There are too few red blood cells .
It may take me a few days .
Could we get an interview ?
If you could just stand ... If you sit there .
- What should I tell ? - Tell it all .
- We are not allowed to ... - I take responsibility .
The main problem for the trolls is that they can not convert vitamin D -
- From sunlight to calcium , like we can .
When they are exposed to bright sunlight , their body reacts .
The stomach swells .
Gas pushes out into the intestines and blood vessels . It is unbearable .
- And then they explode ? - Yes .
- But some trolls calcified ? - Yes , the older trolls calcified .
Their veins are too narrow , so the expansion occurs inside of their bones .
It takes a few seconds , then they turn into limestone and become quite stiff .
I wish they did not have to experience that pain .
It is traumatic , but it only takes a few seconds before they become stiff .
We 'd probably give them a shot .
- I 'll have the answer in a few days - And then you 'll call me ?
- Have a good time . - You too .
- Shall we go ? - Yes .
- Why do you have so many local newspapers ? - I 'm gathering information .
- About what ? - About trolls .
Accidents and things that have happened that trolls are often behind .
- I have the folders back there . - May I see ?
" End of the Road . "
People will always find natural explanations .
But if you know what to look for , it is easy to see that there are trolls .
The bridge is smashed in half .
He waded up the fjord and knocked through the concrete with his head .
There are trolls that large ?
Yes , giant ones can become that large . I 'm the only one who has seen them though .
There is mountain troll territory in Finnmarksvidden .
And then there 's one on the Hardangervidda .
Jotunheimen , three . And then there Dovre .
Now we have to find where the problem lies . Jotunheimen is closest .
We are heading to the first terrirtory with Hans in command .
We are driving in a circle around the territory now .
The territory stops here , and since the tire is still intact -
- Hans says that there haven 't been trolls outside the territory .
Had they been here , there would be damage to the tire .
Smile !
There . Take the shot ...
Trolls love to chew on old tires .
Here , one tried to kick it in , but he did not make a hole in the crate .
- How many trolls exist ? - It is impossible to say .
Do you have any idea ?
Gestation time is like 10-15 years and they usually have only one child .
- Are they mammals ? - Yes .
Let 's see ...
One , two , three , four , five , six , seven , eight .
It does look nice . The stones are where they were before .
Clearly this is a battlefield .
Mountain trolls and forest trolls fought here .
They threw the stones at each other .
But it 's been a while since there has been any activity here .
He will pay back . Isn 't that what they say ?
Do you remember the drawing of the avjotnen ? They live here in Jotunheimen .
- Where ? - Inside the mountain .
- Where are we going ? - Just stay here .
I 've eaten an entire loaf of bread .
Finn is incredibly stubborn .
He claims that all the escaped trolls came from Dovre .
Just because he didn 't see any trolls on the satellite image .
But trolls are not visible on satellite images . It proves nothing !
We are getting to the bottom of this , guys .
We are going to a farm that was in the local news .
Hans believes that it was troll related .
Wow , check that out !
Did you get a shot of that ?
- What happened here ? - It was a tornado .
- Were you here when it happened ? - No .
Do you see how the trees are here ?
Had it been a straight line wind , they would have fallen in one direction .
Who was here and showed you the map ?
They didn 't show any identification .
But they had some fine weather maps and satellite maps of the area .
And we could see something that looked like tornados .
There are traces of at least three trolls here who have continued north .
The fact that people don 't notice these big beasts that smash across the earth !
We 'll come back tonight , take a trip into the woods .
I 'm starting to get tired .
- I don 't like this . - We stick together .
Seriously , Kalle .
We have to go now .
What do you think we should do ?
There are tracks in there .
There are traces of them . They 've been here .
- We can 't stand here alone . - This way !
An abandoned mine .
- They have been here . - I will not fucking go in there !
There are no trolls now .
Come on .
- Are you absolutely sure ? - Yes .
No , there 's no one home .
I must get some troll stink .
- Here . - I 'll take the camera .
Is it rolling ?
It 's not just one troll that lives here .
It 's a whole bunch . A damn hive .
- We can go . - Come on ! Let 's get out !
Let 's go .
Come on !
Someone 's coming !
Get back !
Can we go ?
Go back further !
Quick ! Inside !
Turn off the lights !
I have to get out of here .
- Do you have more of the troll stink ? - No , not here .
Try to relax . Breathe easy .
Relax .
- What 's stressing you out ? - I 'm a Christian !
- We 're going to die ! - Damn !
Don 't fucking start to sweat !
Dear God ...
Shut up !
Run !
Sun !
It still works .
There are more back there . I 'll have to get them later .
He could have said that he was a Christian .
I must find out why the beasts ran away .
I can drive you to the camp site if you want to .
- What are you doing in my car ? - Looking after the footage .
Did you root around in my trailer ?
- Are you filming now ? - No .
- It 's chaos up there . - Shouldn 't you be there then ?
I don 't go into that territory . I don 't .
- Turn off the camera . - It isn 't on .
Why shouldn 't people know about this ?
- What is your job anyway ? - It 's confidential information .
Why shouldn 't people be told what is going on ? People are dieing after all !
Why is this secret ?
- People have a right to know . - No .
- Don 't touch the camera . - This is not your business .
It is my business !
- Get out ! - This isn 't over .
I have to go back and check what happened . If you want to come , it 's okay .
- Yes , we do . - Are you ready for it ?
- Yes . - We 'll continue the filming .
We 'll find a new camera .
Here comes the new cameraman .
- Malica . - Thomas .
So you aren 't Christian ?
- You do not believe in Jesus or God ? - I 'm Muslim .
That 's good .
Muslim , is that okay ?
I don 't know . We 'll see what happens .
- It should be fine . - Shall we shoot the musk oxen ?
No , we won 't .
- So , off we go . - Yes , we might as well .
Let 's get underway .
- Who have you worked for before ? - I 've Worked for NRK and the BBC .
- I have filmed lions in Tanzania . - Lions , yes .
This is the worst I 've ever seen .
Damn .
They 've broken every tree for miles around .
A giant has probably been through here .
A giant of 50-100 meters , which has scared the Dovretrolden away .
A giant in the long run isn 't any good .
Honestly .
All of you believe in trolls ?
Do you think it 's squirrels that have been doing this ?
They had it good in the territory , so ... but the TST put a lid on everything .
They may look like ordinary power lines -
- But they 're energized fences that keep the trolls in place .
I do not understand how they got through here .
There is a team of technicians in Dombas and working power generators .
- Do they know about the trolls ? - No , no .
Have you found any error in the high-voltage in Dovre ?
Errors you say ? If you want to hang up you coats ...
Over here .
Several hundred feet of high voltage cable , bang , straight into the ground . 300,000 volts .
- When did this happen ? - Three weeks ago .
- Do you know how it happened ? - No one knows .
The cable is hurricane proof and it fell down . No , we have no idea how .
- Is this a school assignment ? - Yes . University of Volda .
- Are you a teacher ? - No .
Where is the high voltage wire ?
It goes here
and then north in a loop down here and such .
- Then they go in circles ? - Yes , they go in circles .
Isn 't that a bit weird ?
Yes , a little , maybe .
- Yes , it 's weird . - The flow goes nowhere .
Yes , it goes around .
And it 's in a scenic area .
If a giant has broken through the high voltage fence , something is wrong .
I can drive up to Dovre and try to find the beast .
Up there , the territorial border begins .
It 's a damn treck to set up new towers .
But only protestors and farmers bitch and moan .
I think they 're fine .
They were put out so the trolls would have access to food .
It goes around the entire territory . We 've been in this area .
And here . We haven 't seen evidence of trolls .
I think that we should try this area .
There 's a TST building where we can wait .
Some researchers believe that this has natural explanations ...
They 've measured over 1000 aftershocks ...
Now we 're in the territory .
I got the impression that you normally wouldn 't go into the territory .
Is there any particular reason ?
It was a mountain troll territory up in Strynefjell .
In the seventies , they decided to build tunnels -
- Right where it was teeming with mountain trolls .
The TST and I tried to protest , but it was useless .
Then there was my job to go into the territory and destroy all the trolls .
All there were .
Pregnant females . Children .
Absolute newborns who could not even walk yet .
It was a bloody massacre .
Hans ' whole life has focused exclusively on trolls .
For him , every day was a battle with trolls .
He is , in many ways , a hero here in Norway .
What had we done without him ?
Therefore , it is important that we make this film .
Shoulder .
Are you okay ?
I 'll be back in an hour .
Should we follow ?
He is inordinately large , but I must try .
It sounds as if it has all clicked for him .
So it may be a little difficult .
Your phone 's ringing , Hans .
- Where is it ? - It 's on the seat .
It 's Thomas .
He 's a little busy at the moment . Can I ...
Rabies ?
- The Raglefanten had rabies . - May I speak with Hilde ?
Hi Hilda .
Are you sure ?
Now I 'm starting to understand .
Okay . Yes , you too .
Goodbye .
It wouldn 't surprise me if every one that we met was infected .
He has spread the disease around to both Raglefantene and Dovregubben .
- And even you Thomas . - Me ?
I do not have rabies .
Hello ! Dogs have rabies .
If you have rabies , you need to go to the hospital .
If you think that he has rabies , he must go to the hospital !
I do not have rabies .
You may not know that I have rabies ! Then we have to get to a hospital right away !
- Now comes the damn animals . - I will damn it !
- We can 't be here . - Look !
Is it coming here ?
Go out ? Are you mad ?
He 's leaving !
Stand still ! I 'll try to lure him over here .
What a friend we have in Jesus ...
What 's he doing ?
The damned flash ran out of power .
Definitely rabies .
Can we drive to the hospital now ?
- I should probably give some more flashes . - What are you talking about ?
But first I have to wear him down .
He 's getting closer !
- We 're running from him ! - That 's good .
- There 's a person ! - Stop , Hans !
- Get in ! - Hurry up , dammit !
Go ! Go !
- Where are you going ? - Stay here .
- Hans ! - Get back !
Damn !
Get in the car !
- What are you doing here ? - I 'm a seismologist .
It 's right in front of us .
Watch out !
Is it on now ?
Hans , what are you doing ?
I have to give him the coup de grace .
- With that there ? - Yes .
I hope that I 've got the shots I need .
Follow the road . Then you will come to E6 .
I can 't hear anything !
Malica ...
Don 't make fun of me . There are trolls on these drives .
Here 's the footage .
I 'm bleeding ? What did you say ?
- Are you okay ? - Yes , I 'm fine .
Look ! Look there !
Isn 't that Finn and the others ?
Damn , it is Finn . Camera . Give me the camera !
Thomas , what are you doing ?
Here ends the recording .
Nothing was found in the mine , and the filmmakers vanished without a trace .
We urge anyone who has information
to contact Filmkameratene A / S or the nearest police station .
It has not been possible to obtain confirmation of TST 's existence .
An indirect confirmation came , however -
- From Prime Minister Jens Stoltenberg in Oslo on 25 June 2010 .
The press did not understand the point .
We want to minimize interference in the Norwegian countryside .
He says power lines are fine .
I think not .
But in Norway , we have the power
but against power lines . And it doesn 't last .
Norway has trolls , so it will need more power lines .
- And so it is . - We 'll wrap here !
Translated by : indy99